Finding Aid for Lemuel A. Johnson Papers, 1942-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lemuel A. Johnson papers 1942-2002
Johnson, Lemuel A.
0574 Aa 2
Lemuel A. Johnson (1941-2002) was born in Maiduguri, Nigeria. An expert in African literature and the Diaspora, a literary critic, and poet, he taught English at the Fourah Bay College of the University of Sierra Leone and comparative literature at the University of Michigan. From 1985 to 1991 he served as director of the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies; author of a three-volume work of poems entitled the Sierra Leone Trilogy. and numerous works of literary criticism. Papers include biographical information, correspondence from colleagues and family, and information about his work in the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies and the Department of English Language and Literature. There are also notes and drafts of Johnson's literary criticism, poetry, and his other writings.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated to the library by Mrs. Lemuel Johnson (Donor no. 9578 ) in April 2005. 9578
The collection is open to research.
Lemuel A. Johnson was born on December 15, 1941 in Maiduguri, Nigeria. The son of Sierra Leone natives, Thomas and Daisy Williams Johnson, he was sent to live with his grandparents in Freetown at the age of twelve. There, he was educated at the Sierra Leone Grammar School, the city's most exclusive secondary school. Already fluent in the three languages of Nigeria (Yoruba, Hausa, and Igbo), his family's language Krio, and English, he learned French and Latin. Johnson excelled in all his studies graduating with the highest score ever achieved in Africa on the Cambridge University School Leavers Examination. When Johnson left secondary school (as head boy) in 1961, he was destined to attend Cambridge University. However, the United States government, to celebrate the newly independent status of Sierra Leone, offered eleven scholarships from America's top universities and colleges, such as Harvard, Yale, and the University of California, Los Angeles, to the best Sierra Leone students. Johnson was given one and attended Oberlin College, graduating in 1965 with a degree in modern languages, and mastery of his eighth language, Spanish. He would later develop, at least, reading fluency in German, Italian, Portuguese, and Russian.
While a student at Oberlin, Johnson attended receptions held at the Sierra Leone embassy for Sierra Leonean students living in Canada and the United States. At the 1964 gathering, he met Marian Yankson, who was studying dental hygiene at Howard University. They were married on August 28, 1965, in Washington, D.C.
The government in Sierra Leone expected him to continue his language study at Georgetown University or to study diplomacy at McGill University in Montreal, Canada. Torn between a love of literature and writing and a fascination with languages, Johnson decided that he didn't want to spend the rest of his life in a translator's box at the United Nations. Instead, he decided to go out on his own and earn a master's degree in Spanish and comparative literature from Pennsylvania State University in 1966. He then moved to Ann Arbor to study in the newly established Ph.D program in the University of Michigan's Department of Comparative Literature.
Focused on literature, Johnson became a prolific writer while studying at Michigan. He wrote short stories for Generation, a student-run literary publication. He submitted collections of his short stories and essays and won two Avery Hopwood and Jule Hopwood prizes. He also translated and published two plays, Night and War in the Prado Museum (Spanish Noche DeGuerra en el Museo del Prado) written by Rafael Alberti and The People's Dreamer (Un Sonador Para Un Pueblo) by Antonio Buero Vallejo. The Smithsonian Institution and the Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts produced his translation of Alberti's play in 1971.
During this time he was also writing his doctoral dissertation, tracing "blackness in human form" in Spanish, French, Portuguese, and English literatures. The work for his Ph.D. was completed and the degree was awarded during the summer of 1969. He reworked his dissertation, and, in 1970, published it under the title The Devil, the Gargoyle, and the Buffoon. Johnson's analysis of American and European literatures concluded that for centuries these three caricatures were assigned to Africans and other dark-skinned people of the world, with destructive results for these peoples.
In 1970 Johnson, with Marian and their two American-born children, Yma and Yshelu, returned to Sierra Leone to teach English at Fourah Bay College of the University of Sierra Leone. Occasionally, he wrote columns for the Sierra Leone Daily Mail and hosted a radio show. Johnson became an outspoken critic of the colonial legacy and the social and political systems of post-independence Africa. The government in Freetown grew increasingly unhappy with his criticism, and when the University of Michigan offered him a teaching position as an associate professor in 1974, he and his family returned to the United States to stay (though they made frequent trips to Sierra Leone for visits with family and friends). In 1980 he was promoted to full professor.
Regarded as an exciting and energetic teacher, a careful and enthusiastic researcher, a gifted poet, and a brilliant colleague, Johnson was recognized for his many achievements at the University of Michigan with the presentation of the Faculty Recognition Award by the Board of Regents in 1984. In 1985 he was named director of the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies. He sought to make Black Studies and the center a vibrant part of the intellectual life of the university. He remained director until 1991. In 1992 Johnson was named the Steelcase Research Professor in the Institute for the Humanities.
While Johnson was busy on Michigan's campus, he also found time to serve the international scholarly community. He was president of the African Literature Association from 1977 to 1978 and vice president of the Association of Caribbean Studies from 1983 to 1985. He also served on the Africa Committee of the Social Science Research Council from 1985 to 1990.
During his lifetime he published three volumes of poetry entitled the Sierra Leone Trilogy (1995). These works include Highlife for Caliban (1974) documenting his early years, 1940-1960, many of which he lived in Sierra Leone. These poems, based on the rhythms of traditional Kiro songs, are meditations on his life as a native of Freetown. The second volume Hand on the Navel (1978) records the effects of colonialism on the soldiers of the Royal West Africa Frontier Force as they are sent throughout the world to defend the interests of Great Britain (1900-1940). The third volume is Carnival of the Old Coast (1984). It begins with the discovery of Sierra Leone by the British in 1789 and continues to 1900. It describes the effects of the slave trade on the people of Sierra Leone and beyond into the rest of the world. All of his volumes of poetry are rich with allusions and other languages, requiring his readers to be very well read to understand his voice.
Johnson's early work of literary criticism reflected his interest in African literature and the African Diaspora, he authored numerous works on Shakespeare, including his volume entitled Shakespeare in Africa & Other Venues: Import and the Appropriation of Culture (1998) that discusses how racial, cultural, and ethnic influences affect the interpretation of Shakespeare's universally popular works and how those works affect society. Later, he began an investigation of African eroticism variously titled (en)Countering Traditions of the Erotic in African Narratives (2001 and undated working drafts), Genesis and Genitalia (2001 and undated working drafts) and Genesis and Genitalia: African Literature and Narratives of the Sexual (undated working drafts). He also studied the issue of homosexuality in African culture in No Sweetness Here?: (dis)Counting Homosexuality (1998 working drafts) and Mahmud Bilateral, or (en)Countering Homosexuality (2001 and undated working drafts).
In September 2001 Johnson was diagnosed with cancer. He died on March 12, 2002.
The Lemuel A. Johnson papers (6 linear feet) date from 1942-2002. The papers include biographical information, correspondence from colleagues and family, and information about his work in the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies and the Department of English Language and Literature. There are also notes and drafts of Johnson’s literary criticism, poetry, and his other writings. They are arranged into six series: Biographical Information, Conferences, Correspondence, University of Michigan, Writings, Materials Related to, and Writings.
Subjects:
Johnson, Lemuel A.; African poetry.; Blacks in literature.; Poetry--Black authors--History and criticism.; Sierra Leone--Social life and customs--Poetry.; Africa--In literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan. Center for Afroamerican and African Studies.; Eroticism in literature.; Homosexuality--Africa.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Johnson, Lemuel A.; Oberlin College.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Johnson, Lemuel A.; African poetry.; African literature.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series (.4 linear feet) documents the period from 1942 to 2002. Included in this series are photographs from Johnson's early years in Africa, images taken while he studied at Oberlin, and pictures of him and his family, including his granddaughter. There are also records documenting his study at Sierra Leone Grammar School, Oberlin College, and the University of Michigan, including the August 1969 commencement program and the program awarding his faculty recognition award in 1984.
  - Awards, Faculty Recognition includes Nomination Packet and Program 1984 (Box 1)
  - Campus Events 1976-1977 and undated, featuring Johnson (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1968-2002, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vita 1988-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1965-1986 (Box 1)
  - Master's Thesis Outline undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea undated (Box 1)
  - Oberlin College
    - Alumni News 1986, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    - Reviews and articles about Johnson as a student and alumnus 1960-1969 (Box 1)
    - Student Papers 1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs circa 1942-2001 (Box 1)
  - Poster Announcing Memorial Symposium 2004 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Sierra Leone
    - Fourah Bay College 1980 (Box 1)
    - Freetown Drama Workshop 1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Grammar School
      - Alumni Directory 1996 (Box 1)
      - Certificates 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Commencement Program 1969 (Box 1)
    - Exchange Visitor Status 1971 (Box 1)
- Conferences and Lectures
  The Conferences and Lectures series (.4 linear feet) covers the period from 1971 to 2000. This series includes programs or advertisements for the conferences Johnson attended and, occasionally, his notes or the paper he presented at the conference. The Africa 1995, the Salzburg Seminar, and the World Shakespeare Congress include greater documentation such as photographs, travel and visa arrangements, and correspondence. Johnson was asked to deliver several prestigious lectures throughout the country. Documentation for these lectures frequently includes just a flyer or a program describing the presentation and the occasion. In some cases, however, there are notes or brief outlines of his presentation.
  - Conferences
    - Africa 1995, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - African Culture Festival 1979 (Box 1)
    - African Literature Association 1982 (Box 1)
    - African Music Forum Revitalizing American Music Studies in Higher Education, 2000 (Box 1)
    - African Students Association (University of Windsor) The Moral Vision of African Political Elites, 1977 (Box 1)
    - African Students Association (University of Michigan) Symposium on the Role of African Student Organization on the Development of the Socio-Political Economy of the African Continent, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Association of Caribbean Studies 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Center for Coordination of Ancient and Modern Studies Oral Literature and the Formula, 1974 (Box 1)
    - College Language Association 1993 (Box 1)
    - Commonwealth Francophone Symposium 1977 (Box 1)
    - Conference on the Unity of the Sciences 1983 (Box 1)
    - Emerging Issues in Cultural Relations in an Interdependent World 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Escuela Nacional de Antropologia e Historia Semana: Africa y Latina America Hoy, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Florida International University Conference on Black Culture and Ethnicity, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Friends of Sierra Leone 1998 (Box 1)
    - League of Arab States Afro-Arab Relations in the 1980s, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Medgar Evers College Symposium on Afro-Hispanic Literature, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Museo Nacional de las Culturas and Asociacion Latinoamericana de Estudios de Asia y Africa Las Grandes Obras de las Grandes Culturas, 1990 (Box 1)
    - National Council for Black Studies Maximizing the Interdisciplinary Approach: New Horizons in Curriculum Development, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Pan-African Liaison Committee (P.A.L.C.) Pan-Africanism: The Intervention of Foreign Elements into the Black World, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Saltzburg Seminar Contemporary American Literature, (includes photographs), 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sierra Leone Association for the Promotion of African Culture Week-End Seminar, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - University of Jos, Nigeria Pan-African Conference on Human Rights and Africa's Triple Heritage, 1986 (Box 1)
    - University of Queensland Conference on Black Literatures, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - World Shakespeare Congress Shakespeare and Cultural Traditions, includes paper presented by Johnson, 1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lectures
    - Africa Link, program 1987 (Box 1)
    - Charles Eaton Burch Memorial Lectures, Howard University From Caliban to Friday: A Perspective on 18th Century Literature, program, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Josaphat Kubayanda Memorial Lecture, Ohio State University Native Bodies & Missionary Positions (To Cut or Not to Cut), notes and program, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Professorship, University of Florida Sexual Imagery and Its Import in Wole Soyinka's Death and the King's Horseman, notes, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Institute for the Humanities Roundtable Discussion with Athol Fugard, flyer, 2000 (Box 1)
    - University of New Hampshire Pluralism or the End of History, posters, undated (Box 1)
    - Yale University Council on African Studies Teaching of African Literatures in the United States, flyer, 1988 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1.3 linear feet) dates from 1960 to 2002. Arranged chronologically, the general correspondence includes letters between Johnson and his University of Michigan colleagues and former and current students, as well as colleagues throughout the world. This series also includes family correspondence from his wife and children while he was visiting in Sierra Leone in 1980, correspondence with his sister and brother-in-law regarding an upcoming visit, and other family members regarding family issues and their poetry. In 1995 an email group called Leonenet was formed for Sierra Leone ex-patriots to stay in touch with each other and discuss issues affecting their homeland. Johnson printed out many of the threads of this electronic correspondence. They are arranged chronologically. Also found here are email printouts of Johnson's Africa Book Talk where he discusses African authors such as Athol Fugard and Nobel Prize winner Wole Soyinka; African themes such as Apartheid, the Garden of Eden, and Shakespeare; and issues that Johnson was exploring in his own work, such as African erotica and universal themes such as feminism and oppression. Researchers might consult GEFAME, an on-line scholarly journal promoting communication in the field of African Studies. Volume 1, no. 1 is dedicated to Johnson and his work. The url is http://www.hti.umich.edu/g/gefame/
  - General
    - undated (Box 1)
    - 1961-1976, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - 1977-2001, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - Family 1980-2001 (Box 2)
  - Immigration 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Leonenet (printouts of e-mail correspondence with other Sierra Leoneans discussing issues of interest regarding their homeland and Africa)
    - General E-Mail Correspondence 1995-2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Africa Book Talk, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lumpen Youth Culture and Political Violence: Sierra Leoneans Debate the RUF and the Civil War, 1997 (Box 3)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series (.6 linear feet) is divided into three subseries reflecting Johnson's teaching and involvement at the university. The Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (1972-1998) includes announcements, correspondence dating from 1974 to 1991, and a Ford Foundation grant report. The publications of the center in this collection include articles written by Johnson on the topic of black literature in the Americas. The Department of English Language and Literature (1978-2001) contains syllabi and notes for courses taught by Johnson for the years 1991 through 2001 with several undated. Researchers will also find records from other University of Michigan units including the Royal Shakespeare Company Residence Committee (2000-2001) and the Scientific Club (1990-1999).
  - Center for Afroamerican and African Studies
    - Announcements 1972-1998 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1974-1991 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Meeting Agendas 1988 (Box 3)
    - Ford Foundation Grant Report 1988/89 (Box 3)
    - Publications 1987-1991 (Box 3)
  - Department of English Language and Literature
    - Course Catalogs, Graduate Programs 1979 (Box 3)
    - Courses
      - English 140, An Introduction to Comparative Literature 1998, undated (Box 3)
      - English 217, Introduction to the Literature of the Americas: A Comparative Approach 2001 (Box 3)
      - English 239, What is Literature 1998-2001 (Box 3)
      - English 417
        - African Literatures in European Languages undated (Box 3)
        - Literature in Africa, Literature in the Americas 2001 (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous Titles 2000, undated (Box 3)
      - English 526, The Invention of the Americas 1991 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1978, 1982, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Hayden, Robert
      - Conference 1990 (Box 3)
      - Memorial Service 1980 (Box 3)
    - Hopwood Award Evaluations undated (Box 3)
  - Other University of Michigan Organizations
    - Department of Romance Languages, Program for El Concierto De San Ovidio, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Michigan African Studies Initiative 1999 (Box 3)
    - Rackham Grant 1983 (Box 3)
    - Renaissance High Project 1981 (Box 3)
    - Royal Shakespeare Company Residence Committee 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Scientific Club 1990-1999 (Box 3)
- Writings, Related to
  The Writings, Materials Related to series (.5 linear feet) includes book contracts for The Devil, the Gargoyle, and the Buffoon in 1970 and the Sierra Leone Trilogy dated 1994. Researchers will also find twelve folders of miscellaneous notes (undated, 1980, and 2000) by Johnson relating to his various works of poetry and literary criticism. Because they could not be attributed to a particular work by the processor, they were placed in this series. Reviews of his work will be found in this series under the title of the work critiqued. There are also two vinyl disk 33 1/3 rpm recordings relating to Johnson's work produced by Radio Canada International.
  - Contracts 1970, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Notes (Miscellaneous)
    - undated, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 2000 (Box 3)
  - Outline The African Culture: Essays and Studies, undated (Box 3)
  - Recordings (vinyl disks)
    - The Book of Corporal Bundu (33 1/3 rpm), undated (Box 4)
    - What is African Literature? (33 1/3 rpm), undated (Box 4)
  - Reviews of Johnson's Work
    - Carnival of the Old Coast, 1994, undated (Box 4)
    - The Devil, the Gargoyle, and the Buffoon, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Hand on the Navel, 1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Highlife for Caliban, 1974-1976, undated (Box 4)
    - Shakespeare in Africa, 1998, undated (Box 4)
    - Sierra Leone Trilogy, undated (Box 4)
  - Student Papers discussing Highlife for Caliban, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Symbols 1991, undated (Box 4)
- Writings
  The Writings series (2.9 linear feet) is broken down into seven subseries: articles, criticism, opinion pieces, poetry, reviews, short stories, and translations.
  The criticism subseries (1.4 linear feet) contains the manuscripts of and notes for criticism written by Johnson and documents his wide range of interests. His dissertation on comparative literature and the imagery of blackness is included in the undated manuscripts of The Devil, the Gargoyle, and the Buffoon: Western Literature and the Idea of Blackness in Human Form. There are multiple discussions of Shakespeare's influence in Africa and Africa's influence on Shakespeare. Johnson studied American culture in his outline and manuscript of American Culture, or the Trouble with Babo's Head. His most recent work was on African eroticism, including several drafts of (en)Countering Traditions of the Erotic in African Narratives; Genesis and Genitalia; and Genesis and Genitalia: African Literature and Narratives of the Sexual. There are also several drafts of works dealing with the issue of homosexuality in Africa entitled Native Bodies: (dis)Counting Sex, (en)Countering Homosexuality (undated), No Sweetness Here?: (dis)Counting Homosexuality (1998), and Mahmud Bilateral, or (en)Countering Homosexuality (2001 and undated). He also worked on an examination of nationalist literature from Africa and China in Hottentots, Coolies, and Messiahs: Nationalism and the Response in Literature (The Chinese Experience 1890-1945, and The African Experience 1945-1970). The collection contains only his notes on this subject.
  The poetry subseries (1.3 linear feet) includes the identified notes for and drafts of all three volumes of Johnson's major work the Sierra Leone Trilogy, as well as the introduction. There are also several individual poems in this series. [For Marian] was written to his wife shortly before his death.
  The articles subseries is two folders of newspaper articles, written for the Sierra Leone Daily Mail in 1971, criticizing the colonial legacy left by the British government and the social and political systems established by the Sierra Leone government. The opinion piece contains an article written for the Michigan Daily Weekend discussing institutional racism at the University of Michigan. The reviews subseries contains two folders of reviews of black and African literature written by Johnson from 1981 to 1985. Included is his review of Elliot H. Tokson's book The Popular Image of the Black Man in English Drama, 1550-1688. The short stories subseries contains six folders of short works of fiction written while he was a student at the University of Michigan. Most are in manuscript form, but the Father Northway stories are in the student literary journal Generation. There are two folders of the manuscript version of Lemuel Johnson's translations of the Spanish plays Nighttime and War in the Prado Museum and The People's Dreamer found in the translations subseries.
  - Articles
    - The Pursuit of Excellence, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Purveyors of Mediocrity and Caricature, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Criticism
    - A-beng: (re)Calling the Body In(To) Question, undated (Box 4)
    - Aksident Store, All Part Availebul, undated (Box 4)